Andre Schenker Papers 1983.0008
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
Andre Schenker Papers
undated, 1898-1972
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
1983.0008
12.5 Linear Feet
Andre Schenker was born in 1897 and received his education at the Connecticut Agricultural College (UConn) and Yale University. He was a professor of history at UConn from 1928 - 1965.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated to Archives & Special Collections in 1983 by Mr. Schenker's son.
Location of Copies or Alternate Formats
Digital reproductions of materials in this collection may also be found in the Archives & Special Collections digital repository.
Arrangement
Series I: Radio Broadcasts ( 1935-1949 ) contains the radio broadcast transcripts, including some drafts and manuscripts. The broadcast topics pertain to the events leading to and of World War II and its aftermath. Specific events include D-Day, Pearl Harbor and the death of Franklin Delano Roosevelt. The Radio Broadcasts are arranged by format, transcript or recording. The typescripts are further arranged chronologically within the title of the program (American Legion Peace Program, State College Program, and History in the Headlines). Selections from this series have also been included in the University's contributions to Connecticut History Online.
Series II: Writings ( undated ) include the writings of Schenker and printed materials maintained by him. This series includes typescripts of Why, The Greatest Dates in History, and drafts of untitled writings as well as bibliographies.
Series III: Correspondence ( 1918-1966 ) is the chronological arrangement of Schenker's incoming correspondence from friends, colleagues and former students.
Series IV: University of Connecticut ( 1944-1972 ) includes the existent teaching notes of Schenker. Other documents in the series include a university songbook, campus maps, and a constitution of the alumni association and a certificate of recognition.
Series V: Town of Mansfield ( undated, 1955-1968 ) reflects Mr. Schenker's involvement in town and community affairs including his work with the Young Republicans of Tolland County, and the Town Government Study Committee.
Series VI: Biographical ( undated, 1947 ) contains curriculum vitae and other biographical information sources on Mr. Schenker, as well as photograph, announcements, invitations, five charcoal sketches and one oil painting of Schenker.
Series VII: Newspaper Clippings ( 1934-1969 ) consists of the clippings maintains by Mr. Schenker. These clippings reflect his interest in international and local affairs.
Biography
Andre Schenker was born in Vincennes, Indiana on 28 December 1897, the son of Francois Xavier and Maria (Loeiffer) Schenker. He was a graduate of the Connecticut Agricultural College and Yale University; he also studied at Rutgers and Columbia Universities. He was a professor of history at the University of Connecticut in Storrs from 1928-1965. Schenker received the UConn Alumni Association's first faculty excellence award shortly before his retirement.
For over a decade Andre Schenker was a world affairs commentator for station WTIC in Hartford, CT, ending the broadcasts in 1949. His series of programs during the years of World War II made him one of the best-known commentators in the state.
Schenker was actively involved in the politics of Mansfield, CT, where he resided. He was the founder of the Mansfield Young Republicans and was also involved in political activities on the state level. In 1965, he served as a research aide for the State Constitutional Convention.
Professor Schenker died at the age of 74 on 20 April 1973.
[Additional biographical information is available in Series VI of the collection.]
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to the University, its history, administration, faculty, staff and students. For detailed information on these collections please ask at the Reading Room desk.
Scope and Content
The Andre Schenker papers reflect Mr. Schenker's activities and interests including his radio program on radio station WTIC, his writings on world events and his involvement in the university and town. Some series are more complete than others. For example, the radio broadcast transcripts are apparently complete but there are few records concerning Mr. Schenker's teaching.
In 2007, 5 charcoal sketches and 1 oil painting of Mr. Schenker were added to the collection. The artist was Mr. Schenker's sister, Odile. Additional personal materials were added in 2012.
Military campaigns; World War (1939-1945); Tolland (county); Hawaii (state); Political participation; France (nation); Photographs; School Records; Audiocassettes; Correspondence; Publications (documents); Political parties; Radio stations; Youth; Radio journalism; Pearl Harbor, Attack on (Hawaii: 1941); Notes; History; Connecticut (state); Universities and colleges; Education; Interviews; Manuscripts (document genre); Local government; Young Republicans of Tolland County (Tolland County, Conn.); WTIC (Radio station: Hartford, Conn.); Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945
- Series I: Radio Broadcasts, 1935-1949
  - Transcripts
    - WTIC Schedules and newsletter, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - American Legion Peace Program, 1936-1937 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - State College Program, 1935-1937 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
    - History in the Headlines
      - 1938-1941 (Box 1, Folder 5-36)
      - 1941-1943 (Box 2, Folder 37-60)
      - 1943-1945 (Box 3, Folder 61-90)
      - 1945-1946 (Box 4, Folder 91-116)
      - 1947-1949 (Box 5, Folder 117-153)
  - Sound Recordings, 1937-1945; 16 sound cassettes (Box 6)
    Scope and Content Note
    Recordings include broadcasts made by Schenker as foreign affairs analyst on WTIC. Notable broadcast dates are bombing of Pearl Harbor December 7, 1941; D-Day June 6, 1944; death of Roosevelt April 12, 1945; Peace Program January 26, 1937.
    - American Legion Peace Program, 1937 June 26; (4)
    - Interview Drake Hospital in Japan, 1951 December; (3)
    - Commentary on Death of Roosevelt, 1945 February 12; (3)
    - D-Day, 1944 June 6; (3)
    - Untitled, 1941 December 7; (3)
    - Unidentified albums, undated (Box 7)
    - "History", undated
- Series II: Writings, undated
  - Final Argument for the United States of America on Organizations (Reich Cab; political leadership; S.S.; S.D.; Gestapo; S.A., undated (Box 8, Folder 154)
  - By Schenker
    - Why, undated (Box 8, Folder 155-156)
    - "The Greatest Dates in History", undated (Box 8, Folder 157)
    - Papers, notes, drafts, undated (Box 8, Folder 158-162)
  - Bibliographies and booklets, undated (Box 9, Folder 163)
  - Printed material, undated (Box 9, Folder 164)
- Series III: Correspondence, undated, 1918-1966
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 9, Folder 165)
  - Correspondence, 1918-1966 (Box 9, Folder 166-173)
  - Radio audience letters received, undated (Box 9, Folder 174)
  - Speaking dates, undated (Box 9, Folder 175)
- Series IV: University of Connecticut, 1898-1972
  - Teaching materials, 1944, 1947 (Box 9, Folder 176)
  - General materials, undated (Box 9, Folder 177)
  - C.A.C. history, undated (Box 9, Folder 178-180)
  - C.A.C. history and correspondence, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 181)
  - Names Committee, circa 1963-1972 (Box 9, Folder 182)
  - Phi Kappa Delta, undated (Box 9, Folder 183)
  - Photograph album (with autographs), 1898-1922 (Box 9)
- Series V: Town of Mansfield, undated, 1955-1968
  - Young Republicans of Tolland County, undated (Box 9, Folder 184)
  - Town Government Study Committee, 1955-1968 (Box 9, Folder 185)
  - General materials, undated (Box 9, Folder 186)
- Series VI: Biographical, undated, 1947
  - General materials, undated (Box 9, Folder 187)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 9, Folder 188)
  - Announcements, invitations, diplomas, undated (Box 9, Folder 189-191)
  - 5 sketches (pencil and charcoal) by Odile Schenker, undated, 1947 (Oversize 1)
  - 1 oil painting (unframed) by Odile Schenker, undated (Oversize 2)
- Series VII: Newspaper clippings, 1934-1969
  - 1934-1969 (Box 9, Folder 192-195)